Jeremy Springman

PDRI-DevLab University of Pennsylvania Updated June 2024 ☐: jspr@sas.upenn.edu
☐: web.sas.upenn.edu/jeremyspringman
☐: https://github.com/jrspringman
☐: https://shorturl.at/ixTW8

I am an applied researcher helping donors and civil society strengthen democratic institutions and practices in aid-receiving countries. Currently, I serve as co-PI on the Machine Learning for Peace (ML4P) project, teach a course on data science for global development, and lead several other USAID-funded research projects. To investigate these topics, my research uses machine learning techniques including natural language processing and forecasting and causal inference tools including field and survey experiments. I am particularly interested in developing novel design and measurement strategies to generate rigorous evidence from projects with limited budgets and challenging implementation environments.

Academic Appointments

University of Pennsylvania, PDRI-DevLab

Research Assistant Professor

Senior Research Associate & Director of Civic Research

July 2024 - Present

July 2022 - June 2024

Duke University, DevLab@Duke

Senior Research Associate	July 2021 – June 2022
Post-Doctoral Research Associate	July 2019 – June 2021
Pre-Doctoral Research Associate	January 2019 – July 2019

Education

University of Pennsylvania

Ph.D. in Comparative Politics & International Relations	2019
M.A. in Political Science	2015

University of Pittsburgh

B.A. in Politics & Philosophy (Honors College) 2012

Academic Publications

The Political Economy of NGO Service Provision: Evidence from an Ancillary Field Experiment World Politics, 2022 (DOI: S0043887122000107)

The Effect of Government Repression on Civil Society: Evidence from Cambodia

International Studies Quarterly, 2022 (DOI: sqac028)

First author (with Edmund Malesky, Lucy Right, and Erik Wibbels)

Oil Discoveries and Political Windfalls: Evidence on Presidential Support in Uganda

Political Science Research & Methods, 2023 (DOI: psrm.2023.14)

Second author (with Laura Paler, Guy Grossman, and Jan Pierskalla)

Under Review

Aid Flows and Incumbency Advantage: Evidence from NGO Projects in Uganda Revise & Resubmit at World Politics

The Effect of Government Intervention on the Operational Decisions of NGOs: Evidence from a Survey Experiment in Three Electoral Autocracies

with Erik Wibbels, Maria Nagawa, Graeme Robertson, and Simon Hollerbauer

Selected Policy Reports

Zimbabwe Governance Indicators Analysis Prepared for USAID Zimbabwe March 2024

Resurgent Authoritarian Influence: Evidence from Machine-Generated, Cross-National Data Prepared for USAID Analytic Task on Authoritarian Resurgence and Influence August 2023

Radio and Social Media in Ghana Assessment Report

Prepared for USAID Ghana

July 2023 (DEC ID: coming soon)

The Effect of Social Ties on Engagement & Cohesion: Evidence from Ethiopian University Students Prepared for USAID Innovation, Technology, & Research Hub

April 2023 (DEC ID: PA-021155)

Resiliency Cambodia Impact Evaluation Findings Report

Prepared for USAID Cambodia

August 2022 (DEC ID: PA-00Z-KBD)

Retrospective of USAID's Response to Pandemic-Enabled Democratic Backsliding

Prepared for USAID Democracy, Human Rights, and Governance Center

January 2022 (DEC ID: PA-00Z-6HN)

Policy Writing

Charting a Course for Applied Research in Peacebuilding

First author (with Heather Huntington and Erik Wibbels)

Prepared for United States Institute of Peace

Forthcoming in "A Positive Peace: Towards an Evidence-Based Peacebuilding"

External Awards & Grants

United States Agency for International Development (USAID) Bureau for Policy, Planning, and Learning

Local Evaluation and Evidence Support (LEES): \$98,060

Open Society Foundations

Special Projects & Crisis Response: \$250,000* with Erik Wibbels

USAID Democracy, Human Rights, and Governance Bureau

- Distinguishing Legitimate, Superficial, and Fabricated Anti-corruption Campaigns: \$46,690
- Central American Regional Media Project Impact Evaluation: \$75,554 (Phase 1-2)
- Zimbabwe Governance Indicators Analysis: \$37,894
- Swift Expertise and Grounded Analytics: \$500,000*
- Analytic Task on Authoritarian Resurgence and Influence: \$99,737*
- INSPIRES Flexible Response Funds: \$83,000*

University of Antwerp

For eign Information Manipulation and Interference: \$12,500* with $Erik\ Wibbels$

USAID Ghana Monitoring Evaluation and Learning (MEL) Platform

Radio Station Managers Survey: \$30,000*

USAID Innovation, Technology, and Research Hub

LASER PULSE (with Mesele Mengsteab, Juan Tellez, and David Dow): \$250,000

USAID Mission to Cambodia

Local Organizations—Movement Towards Self-Reliance: \$225,000*

National Science Foundation

2018 - 2019 Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (SES-1747642): \$14,996

Anonymous private philanthropic foundation

2018 Research Grant: \$38,600

American Political Science Association Centennial Grant

2017 - 2018 Grant Recipient: \$1,100

Ongoing Research Projects

Machine Learning for Peace: Co-PI and Director of Civic Research

The Machine Learning for Peace (MLP) produces digital tools that equip donors, policymakers, and civil society with actionable data to track major political events and forecasts about when major crises are likely to inform strategic planning.

Central American Regional Media Project (ReMedios): Lead Investigator

Under the ReMedios activity, DevLab is designing and implementing an evaluation of USAID programming meant to strengthen the capacity and security of journalists and media outlets working on issues related to corruption and government transparency across five countries in Central America.

Teaching & Advising

University of Pennsylvania

Global Development: Intermediate Topics in Politics, Policy, and Data Course website: jrspringman.github.io/psci3200-globaldev/

Spring 2024

Fels Institute of Government Lab Capstone Partner

Spring 2024

Local Evaluation and Evidence Support (LEES): Academic Lead

The LEES activity supports efforts by the Bureau for Policy, Planning, and Learning (PPL) to promote localization of USAID activities by increasing the capacity of local partners and strengthening networks that connect these organizations.

Recent Invited Talks & Events

International Civil Society Centre (Remote)	June, 2024
Schloss Dagstuhl AI for Social Good Seminar (Wadern, Germany)	
Foris International Ethical AI Manifesto Launch Event (Remote)	
World Bank EngageFest Webinar (Remote)	
United States Department of State (Remote)	Jul, 2023
Community of Democracies Group on Enabling and Protecting Civil Society (Remote)	
United Nations Data Strategy Community Series (Remote)	
United States Agency for International Development Tech Tuesdays Series (Remote)	
United States Army 95th Civil Affairs Brigade (Fort Liberty, NC)	
Social Impact Evidence for Impact Webinar Series (Remote)	
Duke Center for International Development US Army Governance Training (Durham, NC)	
United States Agency for International Development DRG Center (Washington, D.C.)	
Vassar College Data Science & Society Colloquium (Poughkeepsie, NY)	
Paris Peace Forum (Paris, France)	Nov, 2022
International Civic Forum (London, UK)	
Big Data for Development & Governance Conference (Philadelphia, PA)	
International Center for Not-for-Profit Law (Remote)	

References

Erik Wibbels Presidential Penn Compact Professor Founder, DevLab@Penn University of Pennsylvania ewibbels@sas.upenn.edu Guy Grossman Associate Professor of Political Science Director, Penn Development Research Initiative University of Pennsylvania ggros@sas.upenn.edu